Finding Aid for L.G. Bates General Store (Elsie, Mich.) records, 1857-1920
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
L.G. Bates General Store (Elsie, Mich.) records 1857-1920
L.G. Bates General Store (Elsie, Mich.)
1.5 linear feet and 5 oversize volumes
85151 Bb.2/2; BB.2 Outsize
Clinton County, Michigan, general store. Business financial records, family correspondence and history, diaries, photograph album of the Sickels-Bates family, and miscellanea.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records came from two family members: Mrs. Ellsworth Haynes (donor no. 5428 ) in 1973 and Mrs. B.L. Bates (donor no. 5691 ) in 1975.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The record group is open to research.
LaMott George Bates was born at Richfield, Summit Co., Ohio, October 13, 1847. About 1852, he moved with his parent to Oberlin, Ohio; then in 1855, the family moved to a plot of land in Fairfield Township in Shiawassee County, about three miles northeast of what became the village of Elsie. Bates returned for a time to Richfield staying with an aunt, and there learned the harness trade. Around 1867, he returned to Elsie, where he joined his father in a harness shop operation. In 1872, L. G. Bates joined with J. F. Hasty, who owned a cooperage, and together they opened a mercantile business. In 1873, Bates married Hannah Amanda Sickels also of Elsie, Michigan. In 1877, having left the partnership with Hasty some years before, Bates accepted Hasty's offer to renew the partnership. Bates accepted, then a year later, bought Hasty's interest in the store, renaming it under his own name, L. G. Bates.
The record group consists of financial records detailing the operation of the L. G. Bates General Store and its predecessor firm, J. F. Hasty and Co. As the dates of some of the records precede the opening of the Hasty store, it is possible that some of the accounts and ledgers are of a Sickel family member. In addition, the collection includes family correspondence, diaries and notebooks probably of Bates, family history and genealogy, photographs, and printed material.
Subjects:
Bates, LaMott G., b. 1847.; Bates family.; Clinton County (Mich.).; General stores--Michigan--Elsie.; Sickels family.; Elsie (Mich.)--Businesses.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Bates family.; Children.; Dentistry--Michigan--Elsie.; Dwellings--Michigan--Elsie.; Elsie (Mich.); Interiors--Dentist office.; Interiors--Michigan--Elsie.; Railroad accidents.; Sickels family.; University of Michigan--Student housing.; Veterans--Michigan--Elsie.; Women.
Genre Terms:
Albums.; Diaries.; Photographs.; Tintypes.
- Business records
  - Account books, 1870-1890
    - 1870-1883 (Volume 1)
    - 1885-1889 (Volume 2)
    - 1889-1890 (Volume 3)
    - 1872-1873 (Box 1)
  - Ledgers, 1872-1920
    - 1898-1906 (Volume 4)
    - 1914-1920 (Volume 5)
    - Ledger, 1872-1878 (Box 1)
  - Daybooks, 1872-1889
    - 1872-1875 (Box 1)
    - 1875-1882 (Box 1)
    - 1887-1889 (Box 1)
  - Cash Summary, 1885-1887 (Box 1)
  - Invoice book, 1884-1887 (Box 1)
  - Business receipts and correspondence, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Family materials
  - Sickels-Bates Family photograph album (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous photographs (Box 1)
  - Diaries, 1900-1901 and undated, 6 volumes (Box 1)
  - Account book (probable Sickel family), ca. 1857-1858 (Box 1)
    (the volume was also used as a scrapbook of miscellaneous general interest clippings)
  - Account book (probable Sickel family), 1864-1865 (Box 1)
    (the volume was also used as a scrapbook for political party tickets)
  - Family history (with photographs) by Bates family member, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Bates Family history and genealogy (Box 2)
  - Reminiscences by Bion Bates (Box 2)
  - Marie Bates correspondence, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Dede Sickels Rankin scrapbook miscellanea (Box 2)
  - L.G. Bates and family correspondence, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - L.G. Bates and family miscellanea (Box 2)
  - L.G. Bates and family news clippings (Box 2)
  - Elsie, Mich. printed material (Box 2)